3-42, Athabasca Hall, Edmonton, Alberta, T6G 2E8, Canada

■ karim.ali@ualberta.ca | A karimali.ca | karimhamdanali | M @karimhamdanali

Research Areas

My primary research interest is to develop and evaluate various program analysis techniques that can be used in practice by exploring three aspects: scalability, precision, and usability. My interests span programming languages and software systems.

Education

Ph.D., Computer Science 2014

UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

- · Advisor: Ondřei Lhoták
- Thesis: The Separate Compilation Assumption
- · Committee: Jan Vitek, Frank Tip, Reid Holmes, and Werner Dietl

MMath, Computer Science 2010

University of Waterloo, Canada

- · Advisor: Raouf Boutaba
- Thesis: Algorizmi A Configurable Virtual Testbed to Generate Datasets for Offline Evaluation of Intrusion Detection Systems
- Reviewers: Ian MacKillop and Urs Hengartner

B.Sc., Computer Science 2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

- · Advisors: Sherif G. Aly and Sherif El-Kassas
- Thesis: A Jabber Framework for Building Communication Capable Java Mobile Applications
- · Minor: Mathematics

Professional Experience

Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

University of Alberta, Canada

Research Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

University of Alberta, Canada

Postdoctoral Researcher, Secure Software Engineering

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

- Designing novel static analyses to detect misuses of cryptographic APIs in software systems
- · Exploring new static analysis techniques that incorporate user feedback in a just-in-time fashion
- Developing various extensions to the IFDS analysis framework

Graduate Research Assistant, Programming Languages Group

UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

• Conducted research for constructing partial static call graphs for Java programs

- Developed various call graph construction algorithms for Scala
- Studied static analysis techniques for various JVM-hosted languages

Graduate Research Assistant, Network Security Research Group

UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

- · Worked on various models of Intrusion Detection Systems: e.g., peer-to-peer, kernel methods
- Developed Algorizmi, an open-source evaluation system for Intrusion Detection Systems

Researcher, Department of Computer Science

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT · Studied new techniques to support location management in Java-based pervasive systems 2007

KARIM ALI · CURRICULUM VITAE 1/6 SEPTEMBER 10, 2018

2008-2009

Jul 2017-Present

Jul 2016-Jul 2017

Oct 2014-Jul 2016

2010-2014

ITWORX, EGYPT

• Redesigned the graphical user interface of the stock brokerage system for Execution Ltd., London, UK

Awards and Honors _

Student's Choice Award

UNIVERSITY OF ALBERTA

ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award 2017

INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM ON SOFTWARE TESTING AND ANALYSIS

Distinguished Artifact Award 2014

EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON OBJECT-ORIENTED PROGRAMMING

David R. Cheriton Scholarship

University of Waterloo, Canada \$20,000

Special Graduate Scholarship2012University of Waterloo, Canada\$2,500

Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology 2012

CANADA \$5,000

Special Graduate Scholarship2011UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA\$1,000

Graduate Entrance Scholarship 2008

University of Waterloo, Canada \$3,000

B.Sc. Summa Cum Laude Honors

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

Best CS Group Graduation Project Award

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

Shell Endowed Scholarship 2003–2007

The American University in Cairo, Egypt 30% off tuition

Professional Service

PROGRAM COMMITTEE ORGANIZATION

SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH) 2018

SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH) 2017

Artifact Evaluation Co-Chair, International Symposium on Engineering Secure Software and Systems (ESSoS)

Demonstration Track Co-Chair, ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE)

Program Committee Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis (SOAP) @ PLDI 2017

PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis

ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming **ISSTA,** International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis

2018

CASCON, International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering 2017

Onward!, ACM International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming and Software 2017

ARTIFACT EVALUATION COMMITTEE MEMBER

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis

PLDI, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation

2015

ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming

2016

ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming 2014

WORKSHOP ORGANIZATION

2008.

Workshop Organization	
Co-Organizer, Program Analysis Hackathon (Panathon) @ ECOOP/ISSTA Co-Organizer, Workshop on Benchmarking (BenchWork) @ ECOOP/ISSTA Co-Organizer, Compiler-Driven Performance Workshop @ CASCON Co-Organizer, WALA Hackathon @ PLDI Co-Organizer, Workshop on Designing Code Analysis Frameworks (DECAF) @ ISSTA Co-Organizer, Workshop on WALA @ PLDI	2018 2018 2017 2017 2016 2015
Reviewer	
TOPLAS, ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems SCP, Science of Computer Programming TSE, IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering	2018 2015 2013
OTHER	
Faculty Mentor, Undergraduate Capstone Open Source Projects (UCOSP) Associate Editor, IEEE Software Blog Web Chair, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) Web Chair, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA) Subreviewer, International Conference on Compiler Construction (CC)	2018–Present 2017–Present 2018 2018 2017
Research Funding	
 Validating the Correct Usage of Cryptography Libraries IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$30,000 	2018–2020
 Scalable and Precise Program Analysis for Modern Software Systems Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$125,000 	2017–2022
 Improving the Inlining Algorithms in the IBM Just-in-Time (JIT) Compiler IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$60,000 	2017–2020
Coarse-Grained Call Graph Analysis of Android Applications Huawei Innovation Research Program (HIRP) With: Sole PI Amount: USD\$46,200 	2017–2018
Publications	
Refereed Journal Articles	
Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, Karim Ali , and Eric Bodden. "Debugging Static Analysis". <i>IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering</i> , (to appear), 2018.	TSE '18
Johannes Späth, Karim Ali , and Eric Bodden. "IDE ^{al} : Efficient and Precise Alias-Aware Dataflow Analysis". <i>PACMPL</i> , 1(OOPSLA), 99:1–99:27, 2017.	OOPSLA '17
Karim Ali , Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Type-Based Call Graph Construction Algorithms for Scala". <i>ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology</i> , 25(1), 9:1–9:43, 2015.	TOSEM '15
Sherif Aly, Sarah Nadi, and Karim Hamdan . "A Java-Based Programming Language Support of Location Management in Pervasive Systems". <i>International Journal of Computer Science and Network Security</i> , 8(6), pp. 329–336, 2008	IJCSNS '08

REFEREED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

Stefan Krüger, Johannes Späth, **Karim Ali**, Eric Bodden, and Mira Mezini. "CrySL: An Extensible Approach to Validating the Correct Usage of Cryptographic APIs". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, 10:1–10:27, 2018.

ECOOP '18

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "VISUFLOW: A Debugging Environment for Static Analyses". *International Conference on Software Engineering (Companion Volume)*, pp. 89–92, 2018.

ICSE '18 Tool Paper

Stefan Krüger, Sarah Nadi, Michael Reif, **Karim Ali**, Mira Mezini, Eric Bodden, Florian Göpfert, Felix Günther, Christian Weinert, Daniel Demmler, and Ram Kamath. "CogniCrypt: Supporting Developers in using Cryptography". *International Conference on Automated Software Engineering*, pp. 931–936, 2017.

ASE '17 Tool Paper

Mona Nashaat, **Karim Ali**, and James Miller. "Detecting Security Vulnerabilities in Object-Oriented PHP Programs". *IEEE International Working Conference on Source Code Analysis and Manipulation*, pp. 159–164, 2017.

SCAM '17

Taylor Lloyd, Artem Chikin, Erick Ochoa, **Karim Ali**, and J Nelson Amaral. "A Case for Better Integration of Host and Target Compilation When Using OpenCL for FPGAs". *International Workshop on FPGAs for Software Programmers*, (to appear), 2017.

FSP '17

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Just-in-Time Static Analysis". *International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis*, pp. 307–317, 2017.

ISSTA '17

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Cheetah: Just-in-Time Taint Analysis for Android Apps". *International Conference on Software Engineering - Companion Volume*, pp. 39–42, 2017.

Distinguished Paper ICSE '17

Tool Paper

Johannes Späth, Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "Boomerang: Demand-Driven Flow-Sensitive, Field-Sensitive, and Context-Sensitive Pointer Analysis". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, 22:1–22:26, 2016.

ECOOP '16

Steven Arzt, Sarah Nadi, **Karim Ali**, Eric Bodden, Sebastian Erdweg, and Mira Mezini. "Towards Secure Integration of Cryptographic Software". *ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on New Ideas in Programming and Reflections on Software at SPLASH*, pp. 1–13, 2015.

Onward! '15

Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Constructing Call Graphs of Scala Programs". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 54–79, 2014.

ECOOP '14
Distinguished Artifact

Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Averroes: Whole-Program Analysis without the Whole Program". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 378–400, 2013.

ECOOP '13

Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Application-Only Call Graph Construction". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 688–712, 2012.

ECOOP '12

OTHER REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

Karim Ali, Issam Aib, and Raouf Boutaba. "P2P-AIS: A P2P Artificial Immune Systems architecture for detecting DDoS flooding attacks". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

GIIS '09

Karim Ali and Raouf Boutaba. "Applying Kernel Methods to Anomaly-based Intrusion Detection Systems". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

GIIS '09

Students

CURRENT

Ifaz Kabir2018-PresentUNIVERSITY OF ALBERTA, CANADAPh.D.

Kristen Newbury 2018–Present

University of Alberta, Canada Master's

Abdul Ali Bangash
University of Alberta, Canada, (co-supervised with Abram Hindle)

2018–Present
Ph.D.

SEPTEMBER 10, 2018 KARIM ALI · CURRICULUM VITAE 4/6

Erick Ochoa 2017-Present UNIVERSITY OF ALBERTA, CANADA, (CO-SUPERVISED WITH JOSÉ NELSON AMARAL) Master's **Johannes Späth** 2015-Present University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden) Ph D Stefan Krüger 2015-Present University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden) Ph.D. 2015-Present University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden) Ph D ALUMNI **Manuel Benz** 2016 TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY Ph.D. at University of Paderborn Master's Thesis: Interprocedural Data Dependency Graphs Michael Appel 2016 TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY • Master's Thesis: Call Graph Summaries for the Android SDK Teaching. INSTRUCTOR CMPUT 497 Foundations of Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada Winter 2019-Present CMPUT 229 Computer Organization and Architecture I, University of Alberta, Canada Winter 2017-Present Fall 2016-Present CMPUT 620 Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada SAS Static Analysis Seminar, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Winter 2015 Co-Instructor APSA Applied Static Analysis, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Spring 2016 SUBSTITUTE LECTURER DECA Designing Code Analyses for Large Software Systems, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Winter 2014 CS 241 Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada Spring 2013 **GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT** CS 241 Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada 2011-2013 CS 444/644 Compiler Construction, University of Waterloo, Canada 2011-2013 CS 446/646 Software Design and Architectures, University of Waterloo, Canada Spring 2011 Computer Networks, University of Waterloo, Canada CS 456/656 2008-2010 Introduction to Programming Principles, University of Waterloo, Canada Winter 2008 CS 125 CS 448 Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt Fall 2007 Undergraduate Teaching Assistant CS 448 Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt Fall 2007 CS 330 Computer Architecture, The American University in Cairo, Egypt 2005-2006 CS 106 Fundamentals of Computer Science, The American University in Cairo, Egypt 2004-2005

Volunteer Work

2016–2018 Fall 2013 Winter 2012 2010–2011 Spring 2007 Spring 2007